All right. So, let's um start working on
this program. So, it says write um I
explained the instructions in the last
video. So, I'm just going to read
through and kind of look for some things
to help me get started. Well, the first
thing I probably should do is put my
name and description. Um calculates GPA
for a semester.
All right. So, we want to write a
program that asks the user what classes
they're taking. So,
I'm going actually leave that comment as
the top comment because I'm going to do
that right underneath. For each class
they are taking, prompt them for a
letter grade and number of credits. That
tells me the very next thing I'm going
to need is probably a for loop for
classes because it says or each class.
That means I'm going to repeat
something. If I'm going to repeat it,
then I probably want a loop. Um, so I'm
going to use a for loop here.
Convert each letter grade to its grade
point value. example a to 4.0 a minus to
3.7. So what we're going to do here is
we're just going to add if statement if
statement
to convert grades.
And then once I'm done, I need to use
this formula um which is you take the
grade point and you multiply it by its
credits and then you divide it by the
sum and then after you sum all that up,
you divide it by the sum of the credits.
Um, I'm probably going to take a loop
that multiplies these together and
uh we'll see what we do from there. But
that means I'm going to need another
loop. So I'm going to say for loop for
calculation
and then after calculating display one
of these exact messages. Um, so then
after that, we'll just need our if
statement.
And that should end us off with our
program. Now I'm going to go through and
see kind of what variables I'm probably
going to need in this program. So it
looks like every time we prompt them, we
do prompt them for a letter grade and a
number of classes. Their letter grade is
going to be a letter and the number of
classes is going to be a number. So I'm
going to create those two variables
here. create variables.
So I'll say let letter grade equal an
empty string for now. Let um num credits
equal zero. And then
um
I'm going to take their letter grade and
convert it to a GPA. So, I probably need
a
GPA um variable.
Um,
and actually,
I need this to be single class GPA
because I'm going to have an overall GPA
variable there. And so, then that means
I need to create an overall. So, I'll
say final GPA and I'll set that equal to
zero.
And it looks like that's most of the
variables I'm going to need. I do know
that I'm going to be asking them for the
number of credits and the letter grade.
Um, so I'm probably going to need two
arrays. Um, because I'm going to be
storing multiple pieces of information
and I don't know how many I'm going to
store. So I can't just say let var one,
let var two, let because I don't know
how many variables I'm going to create.
So, I need two arrays here. So, I'm
going to create those. I'll say let
um and you know, rather than storing
um the letter grade, I'll probably just
store the single class GPA. So, I'll say
class GPA is equal to an empty array.
And then I'll create another one. And
I'm going to call this let um
class weight equal
an empty array. And that's where I'm
going to store the credits for each
class. So I think that's the variables
I'm going to need. I'm going to start
writing my program and we'll see if we
need some more. So we first need to ask
the user for the number of classes
they're taking. So we're going to say um
oh well there we go. We need another
one. Um, but I'm going to create it
right here and give it a value. So,
we're going to say let num classes
equal. Um, and then this is going to be
a prompt. Prompts always return strings.
If you're prompting for a string, you do
need to convert it to a number. Since we
are going to use this in our for loop
later, we're going to want to convert it
to a number. So, I'm going to use
number. And then I'm going to say prompt
um how many classes in this semester.
And then I need to loop through each of
the classes. So I'm going to say four.
Um let I let counter equal zero. Um so
this counter is going to count in my
loop. How long do I want the loop to
run? Well, I want to run it for the
exact number of classes they entered. So
they entered three classes. I want to
ask them for their class three times. If
I start at zero, then I'm going to go 0
1 2 and that will be three times. Um,
and so if they entered the number three,
I want this loop to go from zero to two.
So in other words, I want to run just
less than whatever number they entered.
So I'm going to say keep running this
loop while counter is less than
number of classes. And I'm going to put
a semicolon. And then which direction do
I want to go? Well, if I'm starting at
zero and I want to go up to the number
of classes, then I need to increment. In
order to increment, I could say who I
could say counter equals counter + 1,
which could also be abbreviated as
counter plus= 1, but it also could just
be abbreviated as counter++.
I know I'm going to be taking two inputs
here, so this is going to be a
multi-line for loop, which means I'm
going to need curly braces.
Um, and you know, kind of as I go, I do
like to format my code. So, I'm going to
hold option shift F or alt shift F on a
Windows that format my code. It looks
like it's met whatever formatting I'm
have set for my VS code. So, I'm just
going to leave things be. All right.
In the for loop, oh,
I need an if statement to convert
grades. And I'm going to move that into
the for loop by holding option and
hitting the F arrow. So, well, first I
probably need to get those grades. So I
need to prompt for a letter grade and
the number of credits that it is. So
I'll say let
Oh, actually I've already created the
letter grade variable. So I'll just say
letter grade equals prompt
what is your letter grade or class
and then I'm going to concatenate on the
counter plus one so that the user
doesn't see what is your letter grade
for class zero. um they'll see what is
your letter grade for class one and so
on and so forth. So that'll give us our
letter grade and then we need to figure
out how many credits it was worth. So
we'll say prompt and I'm going to use on
the last one I did concatenation. So on
this one I'll do a formatted string.
It's your choice which one you use. Um
but I'll say okay number of credits is
how many credits was
um and then we'll do dollar sign curly
brace uh counter + one worth and we'll
say how many credits was class counter +
one worth. Now remember this is a prompt
and we are wanting a number here. So we
probably need to convert this to a
number. So, we'll say number
prompt, how many credits was this class
worth? And then we'll close that
parenthesis. So, we're taking a prompt,
converting it to a number, and then
we're storing it in the credits.
So, I'm going to put here gather user
input.
And then here is where I need to put my
if statement for grades.
And I have this in another file. I would
strongly recommend grabbing it from the
last homework assignment where you did
this so you don't have to retype it
again. So, I'm going to come to my
desktop. And I have mine in
uh first website, wherever the heck that
folder went.
There it is. First website. And I have
mine in lettergrade togpa.html.
I meant to open that in Visual Studio
Code, but if you want to copy it and you
like me opened the wrong window,
you can hit command option I or control
shift I, you can come over here to
elements,
can open up the script tag, and I'm just
going to grab this first
um letter grade right here.
So, I'm going to scroll down to the else
and copy it.
come over to Visual Studio Code and
paste it. So there's my if statement for
my letter grade. I'm going to hit option
shift F to format my code. All right.
So first things I want to do is this is
not called letter grade anymore. Letter
grade one, it's called letter grade. So
I'm going to do a command F. And here
I'm going to hit the little drop down
and I'm going to say replace every
instance of letter grade one with letter
grade.
And then I'm going to replace all 11.
And that fixed a lot of the if
statement. The other thing I'm going to
replace is GPA 1.
And I'm going to replace it with um what
did I call it?
I called it single class GPA. Single
class GPA. And I'm going to replace all
of those. And so that should give me an
if statement that meets the requirements
here. and it will convert each unique
class
into the GPA we want. Um, so I'm going
to close my search. What I'm going to do
is I am going to run this and I'm just
going to make sure that it is converting
my GPA as expected. So,
let's go live.
And I don't know why my prompt is off
screen. Well, all right. It looks like
my screen is frozen. So, I'm going to
pause this recording and I will be back
in a minute. Well, that was exciting. I
had to restart my computer. I'm not sure
what happened there, but we'll reload
this page to get our test. Says how many
classes this semester and I'm actually
just going to cancel out of this
dialogue so that we can do this in
debugger mode just to make sure
everything is working. So, I'm going to
come over here to sources and I'm going
to put a break point in our for loop and
reload our page. says, "How many classes
this semester?" I'm going to just test
two. Um, just to make sure everything's
working. So, if number of classes right
now, number of classes is two. That's
great. I'm going to hit the next button.
Um, it's drops into the loop. Says,
"What letter grade for class one?" I'll
enter a. It says, "How many credits was
class one should come up next? And how
many credits was it worth?" Let's just
do three. Um, if we hit the next button,
number of credits is three. letter grade
is, come on, work with me here, it's an
A. So, we should expect it to drop down
and set single class GPA to 4.0. We'll
hit next. Sure enough, it does. Single
GPA is 4.0. The loop increments and we
start over. What is your prompt for
this? Um, let's enter a D minus.
And then it's going to ask us how many
credits it was worth. We'll say it's
worth one.
And then we'll drop into our if
statement. Looks like it does correctly
evaluate this condition. And it does
successfully set um single class GPA to
07. So we know everything's working.
Let's go back over to our code. Let's
stop this and go over to our code and
keep going. Okay. So now that I've got
the letter grade, I do need to add it to
my running array of class GPA. So I'm
going to say class GPA dot push and that
will push this letter grade in to that
array. So we'll put single class GPA and
then the other one we need to do is we
need to figure out what the class weight
was. Well, that's just going to be
whatever uh the number of credits was.
So, we'll say class weight dot push and
um we're going to push in the number of
credits.
Now, class weight implies that there's
only a single class weight being stored
here. So, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to rename this. So, I'm going to
rightclick and then
um right here where it says rename
symbol, I'm going to click that and I'm
going to add an s to the end because
this is multiple weights. And if we do
that and we come down here to the
bottom, we'll see it updated that
reference as well. So now class
weights.push, we're going to push in the
number of credits that it was worth. Um,
and if we've done everything correctly
now, um, this should store an array of
what their grade was as a number. And
this should store an array of what, um,
of how much each class was worth.
So now I need to go look. So the next
thing we need to do is run a for loop
for the calculation.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take this and I'm going to move it up
here under my for loop for the
calculation. So, I can run that
calculation. Whenever you see sum of a
whole bunch of things, that's kind of
just a for loop. So, what we're going to
do is we're going to need to take every
grade point and multiply it by the
number of credits. Um, whenever you hear
every, one thing you could think to do
is to create a for loop. So, I'm going
to create a for loop here, and I'm going
to say let um counter to equal zero. And
then, how long do I want to run this for
loop? Well, I want to run it for every
single grade point. Well, where are the
grade points being stored? They're being
stored in class GPA. So, I want to run
it for just less than class GPA.length.
If there are five letter grades in class
GPA, the length will be five. And we're
going to run 0 1 2 3 4. And that will
give us five total. Um, and then we'll
say counter 2 plus+ because we want to
increment this loop as we go. So,
um, final GPA is going to be what our
final GPA is. But I just realized we
need a running sum of GPA. So, I'm going
to say let running G
GP sum because we're going to say grade
point sum
and we're going to set that equal to
zero. And then down here, what we want
to do is we want to take each grade
point and multiply it by the number of
credits. Well, that means we need to go
into the class GPA to get the grade
points. Um, so what we're going to do is
we're going to go into class GPA at the
counter 2 position. That will give us
whatever the GPA is for the current
iteration. So if we have if we're at
zero, it'll give us the first grade
point. If we're at one, it'll give us
the second grade point and so on and so
forth. And then we want to multiply that
by the number of credits that that class
was worth. Well, if you noticed here, we
pushed in at the exact same time. We
pushed in the grade point and the number
of credits was worth, which means these
arrays are parallel. Which means
whatever is in the zero position of this
array corresponds with what's in the
zero position of this array. Which means
that if we want to multiply a grade
point by its associated credits, all we
need to do is access the exact same
position in both arrays. So what we'll
do is we'll take the class GPA and
multiply at a certain position and
multiply it by class weights at the
exact same position.
So that will give us this part of the
calculation. But in order for us to sum
them over time, we need to add it to
whatever the sum was previously. So the
first time the loop runs, it's going to
be zero. The next time it runs, it's
going to be 0 plus whatever this is plus
whatever it is for the current loop.
Well, if you want to continually add on
to a variable, then you want to use the
plus equal sign. Well, what variable do
we want to continually add on to? Well,
up here, we created a running GP sum,
and that would be a running sum of the
grade points multiplied by their weight.
So, we're going to say running GP sum is
equal to whatever was previously in it
plus all of this new information.
Okay, great. So now we've multiplied
together and we've added them to the
running sum. The other part of this
equation is that we need to sum credits
over time. So actually what we also need
to do up here is we need a sum of
credits. So we'll say let credit sum
equal zero. And so what we want to do is
if the first class they took was three
credits and the second class they took
was two credits, then we want the sum to
be five credits. So basically we want to
take out of the class weights whatever
that is and add it to a running total.
So we're going to do the same thing we
did on the line above except this time
we're going to do it for credit sum.
We're going to say credit sum plus
equals the class weights
at the counter two position. What this
does is it says take whatever the credit
sum was which originally it's going to
be zero and then add in what the new
credit value is. So for the first class
let's say we entered three. 0 + 3 is
three. Second class, we enter two. 3 + 2
is five. And so that should work. Um,
but I'm going to put a comment in here
and I'm going to say calculate the sum
of GP times credits. And then on this
one, I'm going to say keep running sum.
And we'll save that.
Perfect.
All right.
Um, now that we've got all of that
together, let's go test it again. So,
we'll come over here. We know this first
for loop is working, so we don't even
need to test it. Let's reload this page.
Hit cancel. We know the first for loop
is working. Let's double check our
second for loop here. So, we'll reload.
How many classes this semester? Three.
What is the letter grade for class one?
A. How many credits was it worth? Three.
What is the letter grade for class two?
B. How many credits was it worth? Two.
What is the letter grade for class
three? C. How many credits was it worth?
One. All right. So, if we hover over
class GPA, we can see that it's storing
four, three, and two. It converted the A
to a 4.0, the B to a 3.0, and the C to a
2..0. and they are being stored in
exactly that order. The class that was
associated with them, the first one was
worth three credits, the second one was
worth two credits, and the last one was
worth one credit. That means that that
part of our loop works successfully.
Now, we're about to start the next loop.
So, our running GP sum is zero. We do
know that um class GPA is at the counter
two position. Counter 2 hasn't started
yet, but it's going to be zero. Um, we
know that that's four and we're going to
be multiplying it by the associated spot
in the class weights class, which is
three. Four * 3 is 12. So once this loop
runs, this should go from 0 to 12. So
we're going to hit next.
And if we hover over running GP sum, we
get 12. And then we're going to take the
credit sum and add on however many
credits are in the zero position, which
is three. So credit sum should go from 0
to three. When we hit next, credit sum
is now three. We'll iterate on our loop.
Running GP sum is now 18. Uh, credit sum
is now five.
And we'll run our loop one more time.
And now our GP sum is 20 and our credit
sum is six. And then if we hit next, our
loop ends. Okay, so we know that that
loop works correctly. Let's go continue
coding. All right. Now we need to um
there was an additional part to this
statement. GPA is equal to th those
parts divided by that part which means
we need to take this running sum and
divide it by the credit sum.
So to do that we're going to say GPA
or final GPA equals the running grade
point sum divided by the credit sum.
That gives us our final GPA. And then we
take that if statement and I'm going to
go grab it from my last project. So, I'm
going to open up Finder.
Going to go to my desktop. I'm going to
find the first website folder and I'm
going to find where I stored
my old code.
And then I'm going to grab that if
statement. So, I'm going to hit command
option I. Um, I'm actually gonna grab it
from sources this time. And if I scroll
all the way to the bottom, there is my
if statement.
I'm going to copy it.
Come back over here.
Paste it.
And I accidentally put a back tick
there. Get rid of that.
All right.
So, that should give us our total GPA.
Um, and let's see if there's anything
else it wanted us to do. It doesn't look
like it. So, let's just double check
that our GPA calculation is correct. So,
we're going to come over here to our
array project. Reload the page. How many
classes this semester? Three. What is
your letter grade for class one? A. How
many credits was worth? Three. Letter
grade for class 2 B plus two. Letter
grade for class three A. And we'll make
that three credits.
And it broke on this break point. And we
actually don't want to test that. We
want to test our if statement. Oh, and
it can't find a variable total GPA. And
that is because we called ours final
GPA. So our code broke. Let's go fix
that. Right here, you can see why it
broke. It said can't find variable total
GPA. So we're going to come over here
and wherever there's total GPA, we're
going to replace it with final GPA.
Okay. So, I'm going to hit command F,
search for total GPA, and replace it
with final GPA. Going to replace all
five instances, save my code, and go
rerun it. How many classes this
semester? Three. Letter grade for class
one A was worth three credits. Letter
grade for class 2 B+ is worth two
credits. Letter grade for class 3 A,
three credits. And it says your GPA is
3.825. Great job. Your consistent effort
is paying off. Keep challenging yourself
and building on this progress. So, it
looks like everything is working. Um,
all I'm going to do now is clean up. So,
keep my comments. Those comments are
good so far. And I'm just going to
change this from convert letter grade
one to just convert letter grade um to
grade point. Um, right here, I'm going
to say store in parallel
and then run my for loop calculation.
and then if statement for final message.
And then I don't need any of these
comments because these were just
explaining the project.
So if we delete those and save our code
and give it one last look through, it
looks like we are done. And so that
wraps up this project. Thanks for
watching.